Hello and welcome back to Python Core and Applied Concepts for a level data sense workflow.
In the last video we started the discussion about functions, we saw how to know or went
to write functions. I mean we discuss about the scenarios or situations where we think
that we should write function instead of big monolithic code. So what are those hints
that we get when that kind of situation arises when we are sure that we should instead write
a function instead of writing a big monolithic code. This was in our discussion in the last
class. So let me recap it very quickly. So right we started with the discussion around the
need for a function right. So the three previous that we discussed very briefly was how
the usability if you know want your code to be reused again and again by yourself as well as
third party then you should most probably write function and not flat codes. So this was our first
point. Then we talked about decomposition aspects of you know writing function also.
When your task is very difficult or big if you want to solve some you know complex problem
which if you don't decompose into smaller problems becomes really hard to tackle at once.
So that's also a good sign that you should think about functions. You should think about
subproblems as well as solving those subproblems using functions. Then the third point was abstraction
right. The function helps you abstract with the detail of how you implement it. So someone who
wants to use your function need not know all the detail of your function but can work with your
function by you know ingest the interface or the no contract of your function or signature of
your function which looks just like this. So with the proper description of function in
natural language you can you know make other people use your function efficiently without any
problem. This was the abstract view or logical view of the function that again motivates us to
write function in many places where we want other to use our code without being you know bothered
about how the code is actually implemented or how the function is actually implemented.
So we discuss it then we also discuss about the basic syntax and semantics of function
which included how to write functions whatever different you know component of defining a function
like you have a depth and definitely a name for the function followed by body and then there
must be a no return which returns the value that you want this function to detect. This was
no very briefly that we talked about function syntax in the last part then we also said that
this is only the syntax the actual semantics comes when you you know call this function so this
is just definition so when you define things these things are not calculated but when you want to
use this function you call these functions with their name and by passing the actual value for
this parameter which we called no argument to this function to get it to get that is else no
evaluated okay so that that's what we say you know calling the function and we have seen two very
popular you know ways of calling a function by passing arguments one was this positive
positional argument concept where you don't need to explicitly tell what are the arguments that
you are passing I mean you don't need to name the argument but you can just pass the values but
in that case you need to maintain the order in which the function actually defines the parameter
when you pass this argument to the parameter okay so this was no positional way where you can
actually avoid no giving this names of parameter like length width and no color in this case
but you can simply call this function by passing the value to this parameter but you have to maintain
the order in which you know you pass this thing so this is what we discussed in the other cases
when your function may have lot of let's say parameter or arguments defined then you may not
recall the order exact order in which these parameters were defined so in those cases we can
also name the parameters and then pass the value explicitly by saying what these values correspond
or which parameter these values correspond to okay so that is most of the time you know very
convenient for us and we use this in case of any confusion and then there are you know otherwise
where you can mix both positional and keyword arguments together but here when you mix them you
have to no keep in mind that you can only use positional arguments in the beginning and once you
have used any you know keyword argument then from then onward you cannot use positional
arguments so this is one restriction that we have to you know follow when we try to mix them
so depending upon what is your you know what what is your you know exact condition I mean you
can use any of these three way of passing values to function parameters so you know just practice
some no more solving some more problems small problems where functions are naturally
you know more desirable so and try to use these three types of you know argument passing to
you know be confident about using them okay so now we'll continue our discussion and we will talk
about the nature of arguments that we pass to function okay so normally you pass some data
you know as a no argument to the function parameter and those think can be mutable as well as
immutable right we have you know seen that now there are data types like number strings and
tuples which are immutable data types no one use once you define them I mean you cannot change
them so this is what we know mean by immutable so you know you cannot so it cannot be changed
after creation and when functions receives this kind of immutable not types they are essentially
receiving a copy right and you cannot change the original thing by changing that copy so so the
problem that so why we are discussing this is because of you know the side effect that function might
have so when we say side effect we want to know whether the argument that we want we are passing
to the function is the function actually changing those argument or not okay or is it simply you
know using the value of those you know argument which you pass as maybe variable to the function
so this is a very important point to keep in mind when you're writing a function or using a
function which is written by someone else so you want to be sure what are the effects of the
function is does it only return me the result value or it also changes some other variable you
and these things would be very you know explicit okay but in most of the cases you know by the
nature of the argument you can actually guess whether these things will be changed or not so for
example if the arguments are immutable not data types then they will not be changed but then
when arguments are immutable data types for example list dictionary or set in those cases you should
be very careful I mean if you want it not to be changed then you better pass a deep no copy kind
of thing you pass a copy of the actual you know data rather than the whole data itself okay so just
to highlight this I mean I will give you two short examples one for immutable data types and one
for immutable data types and we will be able to see what is the difference you know in the context
of these exact examples so let me write down the very you know first example which
is about immutable data types so for example let's say you want to update you know a score
by some you know margin let's say which we call bonus okay so we can define a small you know
function like this which is let's say definition is no update on maybe score
and then you you pass the original score
and then this bonus bonus is the amount by which I want to update this score so so the implementation
what I do is you know my actual implementation is let's say a score is score
plus okay so the important thing that I want to highlight here is that no see I mean we we are
changing you know one of the argument which is a score right the very first argument which you
pass to this function we are inside the function we are trying to change that you know value
right score to score plus bonus okay so now we want to you know know what is the effect of this
to the let's the original value which has been no pass to us okay so this score you know make
come as a you know variable name to us I mean to this function when it is called so we would like
to analyze and see whether changing it inside the function will actually change the original value
or not so this is no our intention so this this is what the our function does and then let's say
what we return is value score okay now we would like to see what is the effect of this function so
let me you know so this is just the definition of the function so to see the effect we need to
you know call this function so let me call this function and let's say initialize some variable
where we store some initial let's score so this variable original score has some no original score
which you would like to pass this update score function and then update this okay so now
if let's I want to call this function okay and get let's say the new score that I
no one to obtain by updating the current score is is what we call new score here and then we
update the score using update score function and here what I'm passing is this in original
okay so what in just no copy this so the very first argument is original score and then let's say
I mean we want to you know in case it by value 20 okay so I hope you understand the no meaning of
this instruction so what we are doing is we we just defined a function which we called update
score and now we are calling update score with this you know original score value that I have just
no initialize right original score is no hundred so I pass this original score to this one
and then the value by which I want to update it is the second argument right this bonus is this
20 so when I call this function this will certainly return some value right and what is the written
value is the new score that it no calculates and that value I have stored in the new score thing
okay now if we want to let's say no try if you want to see you know what happens to the
the original score that we have defined here after let's say you execute this statement because
no executing you know this statement means calling this function once right this is what we are doing
we are making a call to the function and when you make a call to the function and when you have
passed some arguments I want to see after the call has you know executed successfully what will
happen to the argument value and what is this argument value that we are interested right now
original score okay so to do that I mean what we need to do can we print the value of this
original score so let me uh what we can do is we can say here print let's say
original score maybe you know before function call okay
okay and then I know if I just print what is
score here so we know so what is this original score before no function call and if I want to do
know the same thing uh after the original score has been so let me you know print copy paste the
same thing and I want to see what happened to this original score so after function execution
maybe okay after the function execution if you want to see again now what is my original
score you know this will print okay and we would also like to let's just see the what is the value
of the new score okay so let me you know print that also so
what is our new score after function execution so that value should come in
new score okay so so let me so so the value that it returns in this you know so remember I
mean the new score will have value of this score right which is no calculated here inside this
function so now I want to see what happens to so what do I get in new score and what is the
original score after the function execution okay so if we uh run this piece of code now to see
what happens so what we see is that original score before function call was 100 okay and again
if you want to query your original score so what is the the inside this no original score variable
that we have defined here after this function has been let's execute it so at that moment also
we see that the original score did not change okay so we are safe right because no this original
score contained a data type which was immutable okay so that's how you know that that's what we can
see here clearly right that no we we have this value 100 even after the call but then when you see
the new score I mean you see the updated value 120 okay so what happened no in principle when you
pass this you know a copy of this value was passed which was 100 and that copy was you know
used to assign this new variable score okay the new updated value which is no 100 plus 20 so 120
and this was returned and this value was you know again kept in this new score okay so this is how
this is what is the exact cement takes off how no execution works when you call it with immutable
no data type okay so this variable was not changed this is important to keep in mind okay again
I mean just to no contrast this with mutable data types we will you know take a similar example here
where we will try to work with mutable data type and we'll see what is there so in this case I
mean let's say try to no work with list instead of you know integer so because we know that list
is a mutable data type and let's say we want to no maintain a roster where we want to no list
all the student name okay so no one good function to no maintain that roster will be to add and
use student let's say which which also changes the roster okay so that's why we are no defining
this kind of function so the function that I'm trying to define right now is a new let's say
edition of a student name in the existing roster so let's say what we say is no add student
is what is my you know function that I'm trying to define and the very first
no argument which I pass here is a list I mean I know this is intended to be list right now you
don't know it right because we have not defined the function body so so my intention is to no keep
make this you know roster list okay mutable data type and then given any let's say student name
I would want to no append it to the end of this let's say roster so this is my you know
intention of the function so you can now guess what should be the okay so what should be the
statement that I shall write inside I want to append something to the existing you know roster so
if roster is a list we have already seen this kind of in build function which can
append something to our list and remember that when we discussed list we said that this kind of
our method call will actually change the original list right so so it was called on roster so it
has a side effect of changing the list right it will change your original list so student name is
what we want to add so this most probably you know based on our you know current understanding of
list and its prospective methods we know that this will have a side effect and it will modify the
original list okay so so let me now again I mean do something you know similar as we so so let me
first so this function no need not return anything I mean it's not necessary for every function to
returns explicitly I have a return statement so we'll see that as we go ahead but let me you know
finish it and then what we can have we can again I mean start let's say
so let's say this is our roster class students which if I initialize with you know one student name
let's say Hardik is already in the roster and then I want to maybe add another student so let me
add so let me know use this so I passed the original
the student list to this you know add student function that we have defined just now and just
give one more name as a new entry to this so let's say no no is what I want to add to this
cluster so so what do I want to see now I mean I want to see that no what's the status of this
class student before and after we call this function okay because remember this is the point
where we are actually calling the function right so I want to see what is the effect of execution
of this function on this list class students so to see that I I can actually print it before just
before this one and just after this one right so this is what we can do so what we can say is
let me have a print statement just before it so we want to see what is so before function
equal before function or we want to see what is there in this list which I call class students
okay so what is there you know inside this thing
when I call this no class student so and we want to just have similar things after the execution
of the functions let me copy this and we can again paste the same piece of code here and we can
say is after let's the function call after function call again we want to see what is the status
of the same no list will use the same thing now if we and no this is the original list that we have
created okay so remember that this is the original list that we have created now what do we expect
as an you know outcome when we execute this code and when this function call has been made once
so what is the effect that we want to see here in in this print okay since this is a mutable
not a type we expect that this no roster which is no we which took the value of you know this class
student initially we we expect it to change so this this is what is our expectation and now
to put this on this piece of code and see what happened you see I printed the same
you know variable this class student before and after also and in this case if I print them before
and after I can see a difference because this was a mutable not a type this was list so here I
mean when you pass this you know list to this roster you don't actually pass a copy instead
what you are passing is the you know the actual thing and so if you make a change you your change
is reflected in the other place also okay so this was very you know small to I mean these were two
very small example but very you know you listed above the fact that how function can change
you know the arguments also and you should be very careful if you are passing a mutable argument
then I mean you know for sure that that's not changed right and this is what we saw here let me
printed this original score that we passed you know instead you know in a place of this score
we saw that there was no change right because here initially also we observed 100 and after
the call also we observed 100 but in this case you can see now I use something very you know similar
but no I in this case since the argument was mutable at a time we could see a change before
and after the function call okay so great so with this no now we you know conclude the discussion
of this particular part of function I mean which is about the mutable any mutable at a time now
we want to go to another important concepts which we very often use in the context of function
which is called default argument okay so what a default argument so default arguments are I mean
they allow you to define parameters with preset values in function definitions okay so
sometime you know sometime I mean some of the arguments for a function can be guessed actually
okay so so for example I mean if you are writing some function which has multiple parameter
and some of the parameter always let's say take some values by default you know for most of
the you know function calls then in that case it is a good idea to you know explicitly tell
Python that now these arguments by default take this kind of value so you assume by default
this value if user does not want to specify explicitly some other value so this is the intention
of you know having this kind of not default arguments so default arguments allow you to define
some of the parameters with preset values in function definition okay now if caller does not want to
provide that argument then these default values are used so this is what the you know default this
is what we called default arguments in you know Python and I user need not provide them explicitly
so let me sum to this so what very said this now is what he's mentioned here okay so default
arguments allow you to define parameters with preset values and you know need not actually provide
those value when you're calling no function just I mean against to give it a concrete
context we can start with a simple function and try to see for example let's say if you want to order
a copy okay if you want to order a copy and you know your copy machine has some function inside
it which automates the whole process of let's say making copy for you so
most of the time I mean since no maybe even people are taking lists so when you want to order a
copy you have to specify what is the type of the copy you know what size of copy you want you know
medium or large size or do you want you know sugar or not and if you want sugar how much you know
sugar you want you want little amount I amount or no no amount so all of this now can be
you know should be provided to make you or you can give you no proper copy but then in no
most of the cases we know that most of the people who want to come for copy they prefer let's say
medium size cup and then they also expect some amount of sugar which may be quantified by
let's say if you know no sugar is zero if you know very little sugar is one if no some sugar is
two and then if you know a little more sugar is three then most of the time you know you would say
that we want sugar quantity to be two we want you know size to be medium and then type of the
copy you of course you want to ask from the customer because it varies most of the time based on
your you know past observation so you can actually then define this no order of copy kind of
function inside Python okay let me you know just try to mimic this you know copy thing using a
function so let me if I want to know I don't know function to order this copy so this order
copy function would try to mimic what we said just now let's say okay so we are ordering our
copy and so let's say three things there are three argument that typically you know
people want to choose from one is know the type of the copy let's say we call it not simply type
and then second one is the size of the copy and the size by default let's say I want to
I know and most of the people come and they offer you know order medium size so
if they don't specify I would by default let's consider the size to be medium so so this is
you know my this is the second argument that I have given here is my default argument so this
is how I specify that the default value for this argument should be taken as medium if let's
say user does not specify anything okay so this is the way to indicate that this argument is
not default argument and also about the you know let's a sugar content if user does not
specify anything that I maybe know I want to keep it at a level two okay so let's say your
your sugar amount of sugar is represented by three levels zero one two or four level zero one
so then I want to you know maybe keep two as a you know by default level for making this
copy so and instead of writing the complete no function which actually makes the copy let's
say for you let me you know make it by just returning some I mean just no returning a print
statement maybe that's more than enough for not to simulate this whole thing so what we say
that no we are trying to no give you one you know let's say no by default medium size copy of this
type with no two level of sugar is what you know we want to by default print but if it
now user gives some other value for this type and sugar and you know this size then that will be
printed so what we want to print is just I'm giving you one no some say I mean the size of
coffee and then let's say medium size of coffee what type of coffee that maybe you know
latte or espresso and coffee with some amount of sugar I mean which you can specify or I can take
by default okay so let's say you know this is what I want to return when you call this function
now if you so you certainly have to give one argument right type because type is not a you know
pre-do you know type cannot take any default value because this is not how we have defined this
function so so let's say I mean if I want to call this function using default values of
the argument which is which can take some default value then so the first not in first
attempt what we were doing is we were trying to use the defaults okay so we have to make a
function called so let's say the function call that we make is now order coffee
and then we pass you have to pass at least one parameter okay so let's say the type of the
coffee that now we want to pass first time is let's say call it now that day okay and if you
now order this kind of no coffee and let's say print whatever is returned to us okay
okay so so what do we expect here I mean remember I mean when I make a actual function call which is
this no expression from here to here I'm passing only the first argument right so I'm
no by default this is the positional argument way in which we are passing the argument okay
and we are passing only the first argument so by default it will assign this to time okay and
other two which we are you know sides and no sugar content we have not provided here right if we
we are making a function call where the original function which has been defined has three arguments
but we are passing only one argument so this would work why because we have some default value
if you let's say if you had not defined these things no this portion here and this portion here
then in that case it would not throw some error but since you have defined it to be some no
default value you can expect this to work properly and assign these values by default so now if I
want to maybe no run this and see what's the effect of this run can you see so this is what we
expected right so one medium let it copy with two sugar levels okay so how could it take this
you know medium you know the size because the default value of this size was medium okay so
even if I did not provide anything here it automatically took this medium value for the size
and this you know two value for the sugar level okay so this is how we you know we can
use this default value but I mean I mean since you have written it as a default value I need not
always take default value you can explicitly also you know provide this to the function for example
again I mean in this case let's say let me copy make another function call to the same function
and I may say that this time I need some other copy copy type let's do a special
and I may want to specify that this time you know my size be you know something maybe different
from what is the usual thing I want to large special so I can say this and I want a little less sugar
maybe so then in that case I can specify a sugar level also right because like I can I know
right here you know instead of do the default value I can actually pass this one value okay and now
if you are you know try to print it and see what happens you see our one large espresso copy with
one sugar level so this is how we can use the default argument feature of functions inside
Python no programming language and this no makes your life no easy and it's not it's not only you know
so this is very useful for especially users right because they they can call function with fewer
arguments I mean if they want to accept the default value okay and for most of the you know cases
where you know that the default value will be this it is actually useful right so these are
some benefit of using this default value so one is the flexibility that function can be called
with fewer arguments you have seen right now right we we passed only late and then this function
work perfectly second is no you can actually know somehow we realize this common use cases
you know in a simpler way by just writing this and not asking every time and you know provide
reasonable behavior out of the box I mean even if you don't want to bother user or clear
to line to provide every other detail you can assume those as default value and another no
important thing is this no backward compatibility okay so we'll come to this backward
compatibility soon and see how you know how I mean having default values provides no backward
compatibility in some of the cases okay so adding new parameters without breaking existing code
is what we want to discuss specifically in this in our case so we will talk about no
these things but no let me you know give you another quick example of maybe this kind of no
so so another you know quick example of this default you know argument maybe you know
like scheduling a meeting let's say if you want to schedule a meeting or team meeting or a
zoom meeting so what are the things that you want to specify you know you want to specify why you
are calling for this let's say meeting what should be the no duration for the meeting and who
how many participants let's say you are expecting and whether you want to meet online or offline I
mean so let's say if you are scheduling a meeting and that meeting may be online or offline
that meeting may have some no topic of discussion how how long it should know go so let's say if
you want to write a function to schedule no such a meeting so some of the arguments may you know go
as no default argument for example I mean by default I can you know I may want to assume that my
meeting goes only for maybe you know 60 minutes or my number of participants no by default is no
10 or less and when I'm scheduling it I mean by default I can assume that this is you know online
until I specify it okay so in that case now if you want to write down a function to simulate
this kind of behavior what will be in our function so can we write down something like this let me
here now so what if I you know all right in something like this okay so this is our schedule
meeting you know function that we have written we specify topic we specify also duration
participants and and again I mean here you can see we have specified these you know duration
participant and online as a default argument right so you can only give the topic name and then
call this function right and this will be executed properly I mean there will not be any error when
you try to no run this function or call this function okay so for example like say you know if I
want to just you know call a meeting for let's say daily stand up kind of thing so you can quickly
say that no I want to call this meeting by you know calling this schedule function right so let's say
call this schedule no meeting if I call this schedule meeting with only let's say the topic okay so
let's say I mean topic is now okay so if I don't pass anything else so I pass only the first
argument so the by default no duration will be taken as 60 and participants are expected to be
10 and this should be no online mode okay so that these are the you know arguments value that we
expect to be you know passed on when we call it this way to see what is written I can actually print
this value and then see what happens and this is what we you know expected right so we expected
that so daily stand so this is no daily stand up for a 60 minute 10 people and online mode
now if you want to specify things or you know other things also you can you know maybe you know
call this is a quarterly meeting which should go for a longer period let's say no 120 minutes and
the number of participants are less also more 25 and you don't want it to be on you want it to be
offline so in that case what we can do is we know we can call the same function
with not the default argument but with some other argument so for instance I mean in this case let's say
if I call you know this function with this kind of arguments schedule meeting
no quarterly review and number of participants are 25 duration is 120 minutes and you know this
is not online no this is offline so in that case if I now print it
you can see that no meeting has been scheduled for 120 minutes with 25 people and this is
in person why because this online is false okay and if online is false then I want to
print that this is in person meeting this is you know these are some very simple examples where
you can see that the default argument you know idea in Python especially I mean works very well
and it can be very convenient most of the time when you know what should be the you know most
used let's say value for some of the arguments for your function that you are defined okay so use
now carefully I mean this can be very useful so we don't need to know any other example maybe at
this point so the last thing that I want to know highlight about this default argument is that
it can in some cases help in backward compatibility okay so what is backward compatibility by the
way when we talk about our code let's say you have developed some function okay or you have
developed some library which has many functions written already and you have a large user base also
okay so many people are currently using your library they have already developed many you know
applications software relying on your you know library functions okay now so you have a you know
let's a large user base I mean where your function has already been called multiple times in many
applications which are not running right now okay and now you know suddenly want to maybe
upgrade your function with some new feature okay you think that your function can be you know maybe
made more general or more you know flexible in no dealing with some different kind of you know
scenarios also so in that case you want to you know modify your function okay and you want to
modify it but then I mean if you modify your function you also don't want you know those
earlier calls of the functions to break okay so this is what we call you know compatibility so can
can I know upgrade my let's say library or any function or module that I have written in a safe way
so that if someone else has been using it in no in his application it does not break I mean he does
not you know need to go back to his you know whole applications software and then change the
quote again to just make sure that things work with my no current or the upgraded library so this
is what we call you know backward no compatibility here I mean when we say backward complete this is what
you know I mean so just to give you again a very concrete you know example maybe
so if you don't have let's say no default argument kind of thing you know then
this this kind of things may become a little or I'm not saying that no having the default
argument gives you by default also this no backward compatibility issue you know
you know in all the cases but in most of the cases you can actually use or in many cases you can
use this default argument to solve this no backward compatibility kind of issue so again I mean
as a concrete problem let's start with you know existing function let's say that is already
being used in many places so for instance I mean in this case let me write down a function with
simply no processes some no data and at least I mean it converts you know any upper case into
lower case you know kind of data so this is a data processing kind of function which given any
input converts it into no lower case no strings okay so so a simple definition like this
where we have this plus is data function let's say which takes some data no as input
and it may be you know it calls and this no input this
lower method so data dot lower to just know make it no lower case I mean if you have written
something in upper case and it will be made automatically into the lower case so this function
now let's say I mean this you have no earlier developed this function this this is very simple
function but you know is it I mean just for example we have taken this simple function but it
can be any you know complicated function also so for in this case this has a very simple
role right converts into no lower case so let's say and some you know other you know user have
used your function at multiple places and call it multiple places so let's call it at least once
on this you know let's say hello so if I can copy the same thing and
finished here so let's say so this kind of you know so this is calling this function right this
is the definition of the function this is call of this function now if someone else has written
a you know application program they where this function has been called multiple times in at
multiple places because this is what we are saying that this this function have been you know
called throughout a lot let's say code base so this is our scenario so what happens when we
call this function so what is the immediate effect since we have not defined it we have not
run this block we got this error but if you run it and then it converts into lower case so this
works perfectly and it has been used at multiple times now if you imagine you want to extend this
function by adding some new feature I mean or a new parameter to control this case handling now
in all the cases maybe you don't want to you know you know convert this data processing let's say
function now you want to make it you know you want to add an extra feature which also tells whether to
change the given input into lower case or not I mean let's say so this is the no minimal change
that we can expect at the time to generalize this function or make it more useful to a wider
you know variety of application what we are saying that we want to now extend this function
so let's say instead of so let me copy here
you want to extend the feature or we want to extend this function to add some new feature here
so this should be a good block okay and now I want to explicitly maybe you know give
another option to the user to make it no more you know useful or more generally in or applied
in other cases I want to maybe explicitly know whether I the user want to process this to lower
case or not so here's an option if he you know says true in as a second argument it will be
actually converted to lower case if it says no I mean I mean pulse then in that case I would
say that okay so I would just I mean maybe I made the data itself so I will not process it so
so inside the function you know definition what is the minimal change that I need to do at this
point of time to make it happen so for it to be meaningful what I'm saying is to this lower
to lower indicates the condition which if it is true then only I want to maybe you know
return maybe you know that lower that's why let's say if I want to change the function in a
minimal way like this where I want return data to lower only if this second argument is no
given as true to me in other case I don't want to you know maybe return not at or lower but I
just want to return the data okay now now let's say this is how I want to upgrade my function
okay now if you want to upgrade your function you know in this way so let me define it
so what happens is now since your function no earlier function was you know use at many places
in application no software for many of the no other client that might have used your library
so whenever in all those places where you know this thing was calling it on a single argument it
it may actually so it will start failing right because now you are not the your new function
definition actually expect another argument but that is not you know present in the no previous
function calls previous function call only as no assume one argument and so this should no give
you there a message so let's say I mean if I just to replicate I mean all you know visualize
what happens to the this kind of calls that was already there in some other application now if I
again try to run it you get an error right and it says exactly what we discussed right now that
it's missing one required positional argument which is to lower why because your new function
definition actually ask this no second argument now so so no this is no one very small example to
illustrate that some of modification that you may want or new feature that you may want to add
as a less a new argument to your function which gives maybe more flexibility to your user
may you know cause no error in the existing you know called base if you go without less a default
argument way but now you can actually handle this kind of situation very well by defining this
to lower as a you know default argument so what we can do is we can instead of making this
as a you know normal argument we can make this additional argument that you have added right now
default argument so that I mean user may optionally want to not give the value for this second
argument and in that case the behavior is the default behavior that we were anywhere I mean giving
you know earlier so if you if you can actually map your current you know default behavior to
the previous you know default behavior appropriately then the things will be done so again to be no
more precise I mean in this given case how can we maybe you know handle this situation now for
this particular function so can we you know use default arguments here I mean instead of using
so can we make this too lower to be you know default argument and then have similar value as
the previous you know process data function and not breaking another earlier part of the code
so now we can certainly do it right and we have seen example like this earlier so instead of
saying that the second additional argument that I have you know provided or added to my
process data let's say now function so the first was of course the data but the second one was
to lower which indicated whether to no make it lower case or not okay so instead of saying
that this is a normal argument I can say that this is a so default so I would like to send the
default value may be true whenever user does not want to specify it so this gives user not the
flexibility not to specify this argument while calling this function okay and but still we are
taking some value no which can help us mimic the behavior that we were having in the previous cases
okay so two things are important one is giving user flexibility not to use it and still you know
run it without any error and the second thing is I mean you have to do it in such a way so that the
default value that you pass finally you know converts or translates the function the current
function behavior to the previous function behavior okay so I know I would ask you to verify the
second thing that I told just now I mean one thing is for sure that when you make it default user
can not give this any still run this function without you know any error mess has been thrown to him
but the second thing is whether the you know semantics of this new function is exactly same to the
previous one is what you need to verify after okay now if I you know write something like this
that if so we again I mean take the same definition that we have
we want to if to lower is not true then with that case we want to do a lower case
transformation of the current data otherwise you know in the general case what we want to say is
we want to return the data itself whatever data was given to us okay so now in this case you will
see I mean you you can actually check and see that the behavior is exactly same as the previous
you know function that we have written but now you are providing you know additional feature
in your you know function where the I mean user can control it and pass you know pulse to get
not change the data okay and the so so old code still works and new functionalities I will
be able to the user write without breaking any of the existing let's application software that
you might have you what's the good check of this so a very good check is again I mean call
on the thing that it broke earlier right if you call on this thing you know process data and then
so before that I mean so remember I mean it was breaking earlier right if I don't compile this
you know cell and it still run it should break right it is breaking why because it's taking the
previous value of the no function I mean this is taking this definition of the function so it's
failing but as soon as you you know compile this definition which accepts a default argument and
then maybe we again run this piece of code you see I mean it's not breaking although we have
provided the new feature feature right here it's you know you you have an option of providing
whether you want to convert it to lowercase or not okay I mean you can actually quickly check
whether this new feature has been added or not so it can say is process and data and you provide
something or maybe on the same argument maybe but then I mean if you say that no I I don't want to
know make it lowercase I just want as it is so and in this case if I you know run this function
you see I get the same thing right so this is how we can add new feature you know without breaking
the previous code in many cases by using this default argument okay so this is a very
interesting use case of default argument where and then this is the summary of what we have been
discussing so far on libraries and the first thing that is written is libraries and API maybe used
not thousands of users you have written already something so you don't want to break the
existing function call you know and create this runtime no issues so default arguments provide you
cloud developer to evolve their API or there you know whatever library they have built safely
and I mean especially this is important in public Python library and large scale production
system and those kind of software which are meant to stay for no long right I mean like
you know modules in MATLAB or those kind of you know science tool boxes that you build which
is to be used again and again by user and not developed on top of that so so remember so the key
idea to remember is that default argument allow you to add new parameters to a function while
preserving its original behavior for existing code so this is very very important so this provides you
stability ease of maintenance and minimal refactoring you don't have to go and change again and
again whenever lecture library is updated or know the software on which you have no one
defined your own application software is changed okay so this is the how things you know works
and then there is no one very so we will continue again I mean in the next lecture from here
onward so for today I would like to conclude lecture here thank you very much I'll see you in the next
week